<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - Unit Upgrades for Civilopedia -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PEDIA_CATEGORY_RELIC</Tag>
		<English>Relics</English>
		<French>Relics</French>
		<German>Relikte</German>
		<Italian>Relics</Italian>
		<Spanish>Relics</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIC_IMAGE_OF_EDESSA</Tag>
		<English>The Image of Edessa</English>
		<French>The Image of Edessa</French>
		<German>Das Christusbild von Edessa</German>
		<Italian>L'Immagine di Edessa</Italian>
		<Spanish>La imagen de Edesa</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIC_IMAGE_OF_EDESSA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]According to Christian legend, the Image of Edessa was a holy relic consisting of a square or rectangle of cloth upon which a miraculous image of the face of Jesus was imprinted - the first icon ("image"). In Eastern Orthodoxy, the image is known as the Holy Mandylion, a Byzantine Greek word not applied in any other context. The Keramidion is the name of a "holy tile" imprinted with the face of Christ miraculously transferred by contact with the Mandylion. [PARAGRAPH:1]According to the legend, King Abgar of Edessa wrote to Jesus, asking him to come cure him of an illness. Abgar received an answering letter from Jesus, declining the invitation, but promising a future visit by one of his disciples. This legend was first recorded in the early 4th century by Eusebius of Caesarea, who said that he had transcribed and translated the actual letter in the Syriac chancery documents of the king of Edessa, but who makes no mention of an image. Instead, the apostle "Thaddaeus" is said to have come to Edessa, bearing the words of Jesus, by the virtues of which the king was miraculously healed. [PARAGRAPH:1]The report of an image, which accrued to the legendarium of Abgar, first appears in the Syriac work, the Doctrine of Addai: according to it, the messenger, here called Ananias, was also a painter, and he painted the portrait, which was brought back to Edessa and conserved in the royal palace. [PARAGRAPH:1]The first record of the existence of a physical image in the ancient city of Edessa (now Urfa) was in Evagrius Scholasticus, writing about AD 600, who reports a portrait of Christ, of divine origin, which effected the miraculous aid in the defence of Edessa against the Persians in 544. The image was moved to Constantinople in the 10th century. The cloth disappeared from Constantinople during the Fourth Crusade in 1204, reappearing as a relic in King Louis IX of France's Sainte Chapelle in Paris. It finally disappeared in the French Revolution.</English>
		<French>[TAB]According to Christian legend, the Image of Edessa was a holy relic consisting of a square or rectangle of cloth upon which a miraculous image of the face of Jesus was imprinted - the first icon ("image"). In Eastern Orthodoxy, the image is known as the Holy Mandylion, a Byzantine Greek word not applied in any other context. The Keramidion is the name of a "holy tile" imprinted with the face of Christ miraculously transferred by contact with the Mandylion. [PARAGRAPH:1]According to the legend, King Abgar of Edessa wrote to Jesus, asking him to come cure him of an illness. Abgar received an answering letter from Jesus, declining the invitation, but promising a future visit by one of his disciples. This legend was first recorded in the early 4th century by Eusebius of Caesarea, who said that he had transcribed and translated the actual letter in the Syriac chancery documents of the king of Edessa, but who makes no mention of an image. Instead, the apostle "Thaddaeus" is said to have come to Edessa, bearing the words of Jesus, by the virtues of which the king was miraculously healed. [PARAGRAPH:1]The report of an image, which accrued to the legendarium of Abgar, first appears in the Syriac work, the Doctrine of Addai: according to it, the messenger, here called Ananias, was also a painter, and he painted the portrait, which was brought back to Edessa and conserved in the royal palace. [PARAGRAPH:1]The first record of the existence of a physical image in the ancient city of Edessa (now Urfa) was in Evagrius Scholasticus, writing about AD 600, who reports a portrait of Christ, of divine origin, which effected the miraculous aid in the defence of Edessa against the Persians in 544. The image was moved to Constantinople in the 10th century. The cloth disappeared from Constantinople during the Fourth Crusade in 1204, reappearing as a relic in King Louis IX of France's Sainte Chapelle in Paris. It finally disappeared in the French Revolution.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Der christlichen Legende zufolge war das Bild von Edessa eine heilige Reliquie, die aus einem Quadrat oder Rechteck aus Stoff bestand, auf dem ein wundersames Bild des Antlitzes Jesu eingeprägt war - die erste Ikone ("Bild"). In der östlichen Orthodoxie ist das Bild als "Heiliges Mandylion" bekannt, ein byzantinisches griechisches Wort, das in keinem anderen Kontext verwendet wird. Das Keramidion ist der Name einer "heiligen Fliese", auf der das Antlitz Christi eingeprägt ist, das durch den Kontakt mit dem Mandylion auf wundersame Weise übertragen wurde. [PARAGRAPH:1]Der Legende nach schrieb König Abgar von Edessa an Jesus und bat ihn, ihn von einer Krankheit zu heilen. Abgar erhielt einen Antwortbrief von Jesus, in dem er die Einladung ablehnte, ihm aber einen künftigen Besuch durch einen seiner Jünger versprach. Diese Legende wurde erstmals im frühen 4. Jahrhundert von Eusebius von Cäsarea aufgezeichnet, der sagte, er habe den eigentlichen Brief in den syrischen Kanzleidokumenten des Königs von Edessa transkribiert und übersetzt, ein Bild jedoch nicht erwähnt. Stattdessen soll der Apostel "Thaddäus" nach Edessa gekommen sein und die Worte Jesu überbracht haben, durch deren Tugenden der König auf wundersame Weise geheilt wurde. [PARAGRAPH:1]Der Bericht über ein Bild, das in das Legendarium von Abgar einging, taucht erstmals im syrischen Werk, der Lehre von Addai, auf: Demnach war der Bote, hier Ananias genannt, auch ein Maler, und er malte das Porträt, das nach Edessa zurückgebracht und im königlichen Palast aufbewahrt wurde. [PARAGRAPH:1]Die erste Aufzeichnung der Existenz eines physischen Bildes in der antiken Stadt Edessa (heute Urfa) stammt von Evagrius Scholasticus, der um 600 n. Chr. schrieb und von einem Porträt Christi göttlichen Ursprungs berichtet, das Wunder bewirkte Hilfe bei der Verteidigung von Edessa gegen die Perser im Jahr 544. Das Bild wurde im 10. Jahrhundert nach Konstantinopel verlegt. Das Tuch verschwand während des Vierten Kreuzzugs im Jahr 1204 aus Konstantinopel und tauchte als Reliquie in der Sainte Chapelle von König Ludwig IX. von Frankreich in Paris wieder auf. In der Französischen Revolution verschwand es endgültig.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]According to Christian legend, the Image of Edessa was a holy relic consisting of a square or rectangle of cloth upon which a miraculous image of the face of Jesus was imprinted - the first icon ("image"). In Eastern Orthodoxy, the image is known as the Holy Mandylion, a Byzantine Greek word not applied in any other context. The Keramidion is the name of a "holy tile" imprinted with the face of Christ miraculously transferred by contact with the Mandylion. [PARAGRAPH:1]According to the legend, King Abgar of Edessa wrote to Jesus, asking him to come cure him of an illness. Abgar received an answering letter from Jesus, declining the invitation, but promising a future visit by one of his disciples. This legend was first recorded in the early 4th century by Eusebius of Caesarea, who said that he had transcribed and translated the actual letter in the Syriac chancery documents of the king of Edessa, but who makes no mention of an image. Instead, the apostle "Thaddaeus" is said to have come to Edessa, bearing the words of Jesus, by the virtues of which the king was miraculously healed. [PARAGRAPH:1]The report of an image, which accrued to the legendarium of Abgar, first appears in the Syriac work, the Doctrine of Addai: according to it, the messenger, here called Ananias, was also a painter, and he painted the portrait, which was brought back to Edessa and conserved in the royal palace. [PARAGRAPH:1]The first record of the existence of a physical image in the ancient city of Edessa (now Urfa) was in Evagrius Scholasticus, writing about AD 600, who reports a portrait of Christ, of divine origin, which effected the miraculous aid in the defence of Edessa against the Persians in 544. The image was moved to Constantinople in the 10th century. The cloth disappeared from Constantinople during the Fourth Crusade in 1204, reappearing as a relic in King Louis IX of France's Sainte Chapelle in Paris. It finally disappeared in the French Revolution.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]According to Christian legend, the Image of Edessa was a holy relic consisting of a square or rectangle of cloth upon which a miraculous image of the face of Jesus was imprinted - the first icon ("image"). In Eastern Orthodoxy, the image is known as the Holy Mandylion, a Byzantine Greek word not applied in any other context. The Keramidion is the name of a "holy tile" imprinted with the face of Christ miraculously transferred by contact with the Mandylion. [PARAGRAPH:1]According to the legend, King Abgar of Edessa wrote to Jesus, asking him to come cure him of an illness. Abgar received an answering letter from Jesus, declining the invitation, but promising a future visit by one of his disciples. This legend was first recorded in the early 4th century by Eusebius of Caesarea, who said that he had transcribed and translated the actual letter in the Syriac chancery documents of the king of Edessa, but who makes no mention of an image. Instead, the apostle "Thaddaeus" is said to have come to Edessa, bearing the words of Jesus, by the virtues of which the king was miraculously healed. [PARAGRAPH:1]The report of an image, which accrued to the legendarium of Abgar, first appears in the Syriac work, the Doctrine of Addai: according to it, the messenger, here called Ananias, was also a painter, and he painted the portrait, which was brought back to Edessa and conserved in the royal palace. [PARAGRAPH:1]The first record of the existence of a physical image in the ancient city of Edessa (now Urfa) was in Evagrius Scholasticus, writing about AD 600, who reports a portrait of Christ, of divine origin, which effected the miraculous aid in the defence of Edessa against the Persians in 544. The image was moved to Constantinople in the 10th century. The cloth disappeared from Constantinople during the Fourth Crusade in 1204, reappearing as a relic in King Louis IX of France's Sainte Chapelle in Paris. It finally disappeared in the French Revolution.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIC_HOLY_LANCE</Tag>
		<English>The Holy Lance</English>
		<French>The Holy Lance</French>
		<German>Die Heilige Lanze</German>
		<Italian>The Holy Lance</Italian>
		<Spanish>The Holy Lance</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIC_HOLY_LANCE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Holy Lance (also known as the Spear of Destiny, Holy Spear, Lance of Longinus, Spear of Longinus or Spear of Christ) is the name given to the lance that pierced Jesus' side as he hung on the cross in John's account of the Crucifixion. There have been three or four major relics that are claimed to be the Holy Lance or parts of it. They were, at various times, located in the Jerusalem, Antioch, Constantinople, Echmiadzin (Armenia), Rome, Paris, Prague, Nuremberg and Vienna.</English>
		<French>[TAB]The Holy Lance (also known as the Spear of Destiny, Holy Spear, Lance of Longinus, Spear of Longinus or Spear of Christ) is the name given to the lance that pierced Jesus' side as he hung on the cross in John's account of the Crucifixion. There have been three or four major relics that are claimed to be the Holy Lance or parts of it. They were, at various times, located in the Jerusalem, Antioch, Constantinople, Echmiadzin (Armenia), Rome, Paris, Prague, Nuremberg and Vienna.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Die Heilige Lanze (auch bekannt als Speer des Schicksals, Heiliger Speer, Lanze des Longinus, Speer des Longinus oder Speer Christi) ist der Name der Lanze, die Jesu Seite durchbohrte, als er im Johannesevangelium am Kreuz hing Bericht über die Kreuzigung. Es gab drei oder vier Hauptreliquien, bei denen es sich angeblich um die Heilige Lanze oder Teile davon handelte. Sie befanden sich zu verschiedenen Zeiten in Jerusalem, Antiochia, Konstantinopel, Etschmiadsin (Armenien), Rom, Paris, Prag, Nürnberg und Wien.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]The Holy Lance (also known as the Spear of Destiny, Holy Spear, Lance of Longinus, Spear of Longinus or Spear of Christ) is the name given to the lance that pierced Jesus' side as he hung on the cross in John's account of the Crucifixion. There have been three or four major relics that are claimed to be the Holy Lance or parts of it. They were, at various times, located in the Jerusalem, Antioch, Constantinople, Echmiadzin (Armenia), Rome, Paris, Prague, Nuremberg and Vienna.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]The Holy Lance (also known as the Spear of Destiny, Holy Spear, Lance of Longinus, Spear of Longinus or Spear of Christ) is the name given to the lance that pierced Jesus' side as he hung on the cross in John's account of the Crucifixion. There have been three or four major relics that are claimed to be the Holy Lance or parts of it. They were, at various times, located in the Jerusalem, Antioch, Constantinople, Echmiadzin (Armenia), Rome, Paris, Prague, Nuremberg and Vienna.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>	
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIC_HEAD_OF_JOHN_THE_BAPTIST</Tag>
		<English>The Head of John the Baptist</English>
		<French>The Head of John the Baptist</French>
		<German>Der Kopf von Johannes dem Täufer</German>
		<Italian>The Head of John the Baptist</Italian>
		<Spanish>The Head of John the Baptist</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIC_HEAD_OF_JOHN_THE_BAPTIST_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]According to ancient tradition, the burial-place of John the Baptist was at Sebastia near modern-day Nablus in the West Bank, and mention is made of his relics being honored there around the middle of the fourth century. The historians Rufinus and Theodoretus record that the shrine was desecrated under Julian the Apostate around 362, the bones being partly burned. A portion of the rescued relics were carried to Jerusalem, then to Alexandria, where on 27 May 395, they were laid in the basilica that was newly dedicated to the Forerunner on the former site of the temple of Serapis. The tomb at Sebaste continued, nevertheless, to be visited by pious pilgrims, and St. Jerome bears witness to miracles being worked there. Today, the tomb is housed in the Nabi Yahya Mosque ("John the Baptist Mosque"). [PARAGRAPH:1]What became of the head of John the Baptist is difficult to determine. Nicephorus and Symeon Metaphrastes say that Herodias had it buried in the fortress of Machaerus . Other writers say that it was interred in Herod's palace at Jerusalem; there it was found during the reign of Constantine, and thence secretly taken to Emesa, in Phoenicia, where it was concealed, the place remaining unknown for years, until it was manifested by revelation in 453. [PARAGRAPH:1]Over the centuries, there have been many discrepancies in the various legends and claimed relics throughout the Christian world. Several different locations claim to possess the severed head of John the Baptist.</English>
		<French>[TAB]According to ancient tradition, the burial-place of John the Baptist was at Sebastia near modern-day Nablus in the West Bank, and mention is made of his relics being honored there around the middle of the fourth century. The historians Rufinus and Theodoretus record that the shrine was desecrated under Julian the Apostate around 362, the bones being partly burned. A portion of the rescued relics were carried to Jerusalem, then to Alexandria, where on 27 May 395, they were laid in the basilica that was newly dedicated to the Forerunner on the former site of the temple of Serapis. The tomb at Sebaste continued, nevertheless, to be visited by pious pilgrims, and St. Jerome bears witness to miracles being worked there. Today, the tomb is housed in the Nabi Yahya Mosque ("John the Baptist Mosque"). [PARAGRAPH:1]What became of the head of John the Baptist is difficult to determine. Nicephorus and Symeon Metaphrastes say that Herodias had it buried in the fortress of Machaerus . Other writers say that it was interred in Herod's palace at Jerusalem; there it was found during the reign of Constantine, and thence secretly taken to Emesa, in Phoenicia, where it was concealed, the place remaining unknown for years, until it was manifested by revelation in 453. [PARAGRAPH:1]Over the centuries, there have been many discrepancies in the various legends and claimed relics throughout the Christian world. Several different locations claim to possess the severed head of John the Baptist.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Einer alten Überlieferung zufolge befand sich die Grabstätte von Johannes dem Täufer in Sebastia in der Nähe des heutigen Nablus im Westjordanland, und es wird erwähnt, dass seine Reliquien dort um die Mitte des vierten Jahrhunderts verehrt wurden. Die Historiker Rufinus und Theodoretus berichten, dass das Heiligtum um 362 unter Julian dem Abtrünnigen geschändet wurde, wobei die Knochen teilweise verbrannt wurden. Ein Teil der geretteten Reliquien wurde nach Jerusalem und dann nach Alexandria gebracht, wo sie am 27. Mai 395 in der neu dem Vorläufer geweihten Basilika an der Stelle des ehemaligen Serapis-Tempels beigesetzt wurden. Das Grab von Sebaste wurde jedoch weiterhin von frommen Pilgern besucht, und der heilige Hieronymus zeugt von Wundern, die dort gewirkt wurden. Heute befindet sich das Grab in der Nabi-Yahya-Moschee ("Johannes-der-Täufer-Moschee"). [PARAGRAPH:1]Was aus dem Kopf von Johannes dem Täufer wurde, ist schwer zu bestimmen. Nikephorus und Symeon Metaphrastes sagen, dass Herodias es in der Festung des Machaerus begraben ließ. Andere Autoren sagen, dass es im Palast des Herodes in Jerusalem beigesetzt wurde; Dort wurde es während der Herrschaft Konstantins gefunden und von dort heimlich nach Emesa in Phönizien gebracht, wo es versteckt wurde. Der Ort blieb jahrelang unbekannt, bis es 453 durch Offenbarung offenbart wurde. [PARAGRAPH:1] Im Laufe der Jahrhunderte wurde es In der gesamten christlichen Welt gab es viele Diskrepanzen zwischen den verschiedenen Legenden und beanspruchten Reliquien. Mehrere verschiedene Orte behaupten, den abgetrennten Kopf von Johannes dem Täufer zu besitzen.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]According to ancient tradition, the burial-place of John the Baptist was at Sebastia near modern-day Nablus in the West Bank, and mention is made of his relics being honored there around the middle of the fourth century. The historians Rufinus and Theodoretus record that the shrine was desecrated under Julian the Apostate around 362, the bones being partly burned. A portion of the rescued relics were carried to Jerusalem, then to Alexandria, where on 27 May 395, they were laid in the basilica that was newly dedicated to the Forerunner on the former site of the temple of Serapis. The tomb at Sebaste continued, nevertheless, to be visited by pious pilgrims, and St. Jerome bears witness to miracles being worked there. Today, the tomb is housed in the Nabi Yahya Mosque ("John the Baptist Mosque"). [PARAGRAPH:1]What became of the head of John the Baptist is difficult to determine. Nicephorus and Symeon Metaphrastes say that Herodias had it buried in the fortress of Machaerus . Other writers say that it was interred in Herod's palace at Jerusalem; there it was found during the reign of Constantine, and thence secretly taken to Emesa, in Phoenicia, where it was concealed, the place remaining unknown for years, until it was manifested by revelation in 453. [PARAGRAPH:1]Over the centuries, there have been many discrepancies in the various legends and claimed relics throughout the Christian world. Several different locations claim to possess the severed head of John the Baptist.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]According to ancient tradition, the burial-place of John the Baptist was at Sebastia near modern-day Nablus in the West Bank, and mention is made of his relics being honored there around the middle of the fourth century. The historians Rufinus and Theodoretus record that the shrine was desecrated under Julian the Apostate around 362, the bones being partly burned. A portion of the rescued relics were carried to Jerusalem, then to Alexandria, where on 27 May 395, they were laid in the basilica that was newly dedicated to the Forerunner on the former site of the temple of Serapis. The tomb at Sebaste continued, nevertheless, to be visited by pious pilgrims, and St. Jerome bears witness to miracles being worked there. Today, the tomb is housed in the Nabi Yahya Mosque ("John the Baptist Mosque"). [PARAGRAPH:1]What became of the head of John the Baptist is difficult to determine. Nicephorus and Symeon Metaphrastes say that Herodias had it buried in the fortress of Machaerus . Other writers say that it was interred in Herod's palace at Jerusalem; there it was found during the reign of Constantine, and thence secretly taken to Emesa, in Phoenicia, where it was concealed, the place remaining unknown for years, until it was manifested by revelation in 453. [PARAGRAPH:1]Over the centuries, there have been many discrepancies in the various legends and claimed relics throughout the Christian world. Several different locations claim to possess the severed head of John the Baptist.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>	
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIC_TRUE_CROSS</Tag>
		<English>The True Cross</English>
		<French>The True Cross</French>
		<German>Das Wahre Kreuz</German>
		<Italian>The True Cross</Italian>
		<Spanish>The True Cross</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIC_TRUE_CROSS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The True Cross is the name for physical remnants which, by a Christian tradition, are believed to be from the cross upon which Jesus was crucified. [PARAGRAPH:1]According to post-Nicene historians, Socrates Scholasticus and others, the Empress Helena (c. AD 250 - c. AD 330), mother of Constantine, the first Christian Emperor of Rome, travelled to the Holy Land, dated by modern historians in 326-28, founding churches and establishing relief agencies for the poor. It was afterwards claimed, in the later fourth-century history by Gelasius of Caesarea followed by Rufinus' additions to Eusebius' Ecclesiastical History, that she discovered the hiding place of three crosses, believed to be used at the crucifixion of Jesus and the two thieves - St. Dismas and Gestas - who were executed with him, and that through a miracle it was revealed which of the three was the True Cross. [PARAGRAPH:1]The silver reliquary that was left at the Basilica of the Holy Sepulchre in care of the bishop of Jerusalem was exhibited periodically to the faithful. In 614 the Sassanid Emperor Khosrau II removed the part of the cross as a trophy, when he captured Jerusalem. Thirteen years later, in 628, the Byzantine Emperor Heraclius defeated Khosrau and regained the relic from Shahrbaraz. He placed the cross in Constantinople at first, and took it back to Jerusalem on 21 March 630. Around 1009, Christians in Jerusalem hid part of the cross and it remained hidden until the city was taken by the European knights of the First Crusade. Arnulf Malecorne, the first Latin Patriarch of Jerusalem, had the Greek Orthodox priests who were in possession of the Cross tortured in order to reveal its position. The relic that Arnulf discovered was a small fragment of wood embedded in a golden cross, and it became the most sacred relic of the Latin Kingdom of Jerusalem, with none of the controversy that had followed their discovery of the Holy Lance in Antioch. It was housed in the Church of the Holy Sepulchre under the protection of the Latin Patriarch, who marched with it ahead of the army before every battle. [PARAGRAPH:1]It was captured by Saladin during the Battle of Hattin in 1187, and while some Christian rulers, like Richard the Lionheart, Byzantine emperor Isaac II Angelos and Tamar, Queen of Georgia, sought to ransom it from Saladin, the cross was not returned and subsequently disappeared from historical records.</English>
		<French>[TAB]The True Cross is the name for physical remnants which, by a Christian tradition, are believed to be from the cross upon which Jesus was crucified. [PARAGRAPH:1]According to post-Nicene historians, Socrates Scholasticus and others, the Empress Helena (c. AD 250 - c. AD 330), mother of Constantine, the first Christian Emperor of Rome, travelled to the Holy Land, dated by modern historians in 326-28, founding churches and establishing relief agencies for the poor. It was afterwards claimed, in the later fourth-century history by Gelasius of Caesarea followed by Rufinus' additions to Eusebius' Ecclesiastical History, that she discovered the hiding place of three crosses, believed to be used at the crucifixion of Jesus and the two thieves - St. Dismas and Gestas - who were executed with him, and that through a miracle it was revealed which of the three was the True Cross. [PARAGRAPH:1]The silver reliquary that was left at the Basilica of the Holy Sepulchre in care of the bishop of Jerusalem was exhibited periodically to the faithful. In 614 the Sassanid Emperor Khosrau II removed the part of the cross as a trophy, when he captured Jerusalem. Thirteen years later, in 628, the Byzantine Emperor Heraclius defeated Khosrau and regained the relic from Shahrbaraz. He placed the cross in Constantinople at first, and took it back to Jerusalem on 21 March 630. Around 1009, Christians in Jerusalem hid part of the cross and it remained hidden until the city was taken by the European knights of the First Crusade. Arnulf Malecorne, the first Latin Patriarch of Jerusalem, had the Greek Orthodox priests who were in possession of the Cross tortured in order to reveal its position. The relic that Arnulf discovered was a small fragment of wood embedded in a golden cross, and it became the most sacred relic of the Latin Kingdom of Jerusalem, with none of the controversy that had followed their discovery of the Holy Lance in Antioch. It was housed in the Church of the Holy Sepulchre under the protection of the Latin Patriarch, who marched with it ahead of the army before every battle. [PARAGRAPH:1]It was captured by Saladin during the Battle of Hattin in 1187, and while some Christian rulers, like Richard the Lionheart, Byzantine emperor Isaac II Angelos and Tamar, Queen of Georgia, sought to ransom it from Saladin, the cross was not returned and subsequently disappeared from historical records.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Das Wahre Kreuz ist die Bezeichnung für physische Überreste, von denen eine christliche Tradition annimmt, dass sie vom Kreuz stammen, an dem Jesus gekreuzigt wurde. [PARAGRAPH:1]Nach Angaben von post-nicänischen Historikern, Sokrates Scholasticus und anderen, reiste die Kaiserin Helena (ca. 250 n. Chr. - ca. 330 n. Chr.), Mutter von Konstantin, dem ersten christlichen Kaiser von Rom, ins Heilige Land, datiert von modernen Historikern in den Jahren 326-28, die Gründung von Kirchen und die Einrichtung von Hilfsorganisationen für die Armen. Später wurde in der späteren Geschichte des vierten Jahrhunderts von Gelasius von Cäsarea, gefolgt von Rufinus' Ergänzungen zur Kirchengeschichte des Eusebius, behauptet, sie habe das Versteck von drei Kreuzen entdeckt, die vermutlich bei der Kreuzigung Jesu und der beiden Diebe verwendet wurden - St. Dismas und Gestas - die mit ihm hingerichtet wurden, und dass durch ein Wunder enthüllt wurde, welches der drei das wahre Kreuz war. [PARAGRAPH:1]Das silberne Reliquiar, das in der Grabesbasilika in der Obhut des Bischofs von Jerusalem zurückgelassen wurde, wurde regelmäßig den Gläubigen ausgestellt. Im Jahr 614 entfernte der sassanidische Kaiser Khosrau II. den Teil des Kreuzes als Trophäe, als er Jerusalem eroberte. Dreizehn Jahre später, im Jahr 628, besiegte der byzantinische Kaiser Heraklius Chosrau und erlangte die Reliquie von Shahrbaraz zurück. Er stellte das Kreuz zunächst in Konstantinopel auf und brachte es am 21. März 630 nach Jerusalem zurück. Um 1009 versteckten Christen in Jerusalem einen Teil des Kreuzes und es blieb verborgen, bis die Stadt von den europäischen Rittern des Ersten Kreuzzugs eingenommen wurde. Arnulf Malecorne, der erste lateinische Patriarch von Jerusalem, ließ die griechisch-orthodoxen Priester, die das Kreuz besaßen, foltern, um seine Position preiszugeben. Das Relikt, das Arnulf entdeckte, war ein kleines Holzfragment, das in ein goldenes Kreuz eingebettet war, und es wurde zum heiligsten Relikt des lateinischen Königreichs Jerusalem, ohne die Kontroversen, die nach der Entdeckung der Heiligen Lanze in Antiochia aufgetreten waren. Es wurde in der Grabeskirche unter dem Schutz des lateinischen Patriarchen untergebracht, der vor jeder Schlacht mit ihm vor der Armee marschierte. [PARAGRAPH:1]Es wurde von Saladin während der Schlacht von Hattin im Jahr 1187 erobert, und während einige christliche Herrscher, wie Richard Löwenherz, der byzantinische Kaiser Isaak II. Angelos und Tamar, Königin von Georgien, versuchten, es von Saladin, dem Kreuz, freizukaufen wurde nicht zurückgegeben und verschwand anschließend aus den historischen Aufzeichnungen.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]The True Cross is the name for physical remnants which, by a Christian tradition, are believed to be from the cross upon which Jesus was crucified. [PARAGRAPH:1]According to post-Nicene historians, Socrates Scholasticus and others, the Empress Helena (c. AD 250 - c. AD 330), mother of Constantine, the first Christian Emperor of Rome, travelled to the Holy Land, dated by modern historians in 326-28, founding churches and establishing relief agencies for the poor. It was afterwards claimed, in the later fourth-century history by Gelasius of Caesarea followed by Rufinus' additions to Eusebius' Ecclesiastical History, that she discovered the hiding place of three crosses, believed to be used at the crucifixion of Jesus and the two thieves - St. Dismas and Gestas - who were executed with him, and that through a miracle it was revealed which of the three was the True Cross. [PARAGRAPH:1]The silver reliquary that was left at the Basilica of the Holy Sepulchre in care of the bishop of Jerusalem was exhibited periodically to the faithful. In 614 the Sassanid Emperor Khosrau II removed the part of the cross as a trophy, when he captured Jerusalem. Thirteen years later, in 628, the Byzantine Emperor Heraclius defeated Khosrau and regained the relic from Shahrbaraz. He placed the cross in Constantinople at first, and took it back to Jerusalem on 21 March 630. Around 1009, Christians in Jerusalem hid part of the cross and it remained hidden until the city was taken by the European knights of the First Crusade. Arnulf Malecorne, the first Latin Patriarch of Jerusalem, had the Greek Orthodox priests who were in possession of the Cross tortured in order to reveal its position. The relic that Arnulf discovered was a small fragment of wood embedded in a golden cross, and it became the most sacred relic of the Latin Kingdom of Jerusalem, with none of the controversy that had followed their discovery of the Holy Lance in Antioch. It was housed in the Church of the Holy Sepulchre under the protection of the Latin Patriarch, who marched with it ahead of the army before every battle. [PARAGRAPH:1]It was captured by Saladin during the Battle of Hattin in 1187, and while some Christian rulers, like Richard the Lionheart, Byzantine emperor Isaac II Angelos and Tamar, Queen of Georgia, sought to ransom it from Saladin, the cross was not returned and subsequently disappeared from historical records.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]The True Cross is the name for physical remnants which, by a Christian tradition, are believed to be from the cross upon which Jesus was crucified. [PARAGRAPH:1]According to post-Nicene historians, Socrates Scholasticus and others, the Empress Helena (c. AD 250 - c. AD 330), mother of Constantine, the first Christian Emperor of Rome, travelled to the Holy Land, dated by modern historians in 326-28, founding churches and establishing relief agencies for the poor. It was afterwards claimed, in the later fourth-century history by Gelasius of Caesarea followed by Rufinus' additions to Eusebius' Ecclesiastical History, that she discovered the hiding place of three crosses, believed to be used at the crucifixion of Jesus and the two thieves - St. Dismas and Gestas - who were executed with him, and that through a miracle it was revealed which of the three was the True Cross. [PARAGRAPH:1]The silver reliquary that was left at the Basilica of the Holy Sepulchre in care of the bishop of Jerusalem was exhibited periodically to the faithful. In 614 the Sassanid Emperor Khosrau II removed the part of the cross as a trophy, when he captured Jerusalem. Thirteen years later, in 628, the Byzantine Emperor Heraclius defeated Khosrau and regained the relic from Shahrbaraz. He placed the cross in Constantinople at first, and took it back to Jerusalem on 21 March 630. Around 1009, Christians in Jerusalem hid part of the cross and it remained hidden until the city was taken by the European knights of the First Crusade. Arnulf Malecorne, the first Latin Patriarch of Jerusalem, had the Greek Orthodox priests who were in possession of the Cross tortured in order to reveal its position. The relic that Arnulf discovered was a small fragment of wood embedded in a golden cross, and it became the most sacred relic of the Latin Kingdom of Jerusalem, with none of the controversy that had followed their discovery of the Holy Lance in Antioch. It was housed in the Church of the Holy Sepulchre under the protection of the Latin Patriarch, who marched with it ahead of the army before every battle. [PARAGRAPH:1]It was captured by Saladin during the Battle of Hattin in 1187, and while some Christian rulers, like Richard the Lionheart, Byzantine emperor Isaac II Angelos and Tamar, Queen of Georgia, sought to ransom it from Saladin, the cross was not returned and subsequently disappeared from historical records.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>	
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIC_BONES_OF_THE_MAGI</Tag>
		<English>The Bones of the Magi</English>
		<French>The Bones of the Magi</French>
		<German>Die Gebeine der Drei Magier</German>
		<Italian>The Bones of the Magi</Italian>
		<Spanish>The Bones of the Magi</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIC_BONES_OF_THE_MAGI_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The alleged "relics of the Magi" (the Three Kings or the Three Wise Men in Christian tradition) were originally situated at Constantinople, but brought to Milan by Eustorgius I, the city's bishop, in 344. The relics of the Magi were taken from Milan by Holy Roman Emperor Fredrick Barbarossa and given to the Archbishop of Cologne, Rainald of Dassel in 1164. The Three Kings have since attracted a constant stream of pilgrims to Cologne. [PARAGRAPH:1]According to Iranian tradition, the Magi who visited the infant Jesus traveled from Saveh, and are buried among its ruins. Marco Polo described the tombs of the Magi in his travel book, Il Milione.</English>
		<French>[TAB]The alleged "relics of the Magi" (the Three Kings or the Three Wise Men in Christian tradition) were originally situated at Constantinople, but brought to Milan by Eustorgius I, the city's bishop, in 344. The relics of the Magi were taken from Milan by Holy Roman Emperor Fredrick Barbarossa and given to the Archbishop of Cologne, Rainald of Dassel in 1164. The Three Kings have since attracted a constant stream of pilgrims to Cologne. [PARAGRAPH:1]According to Iranian tradition, the Magi who visited the infant Jesus traveled from Saveh, and are buried among its ruins. Marco Polo described the tombs of the Magi in his travel book, Il Milione.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Die "Reliquien der Heiligen Drei Könige" (die Heiligen Drei Könige oder die Heiligen Drei Könige in der christlichen Tradition) befanden sich ursprünglich in Konstantinopel, wurden aber 344 von Eustorgius I., dem Bischof der Stadt, nach Mailand gebracht. Die Reliquien der Heiligen Drei Könige wurden vom römisch-deutschen Kaiser Friedrich Barbarossa aus Mailand mitgenommen und 1164 dem Kölner Erzbischof Rainald von Dassel geschenkt. Die Heiligen Heiligen Drei Könige lockten seitdem einen stetigen Strom von Pilgern nach Köln. [PARAGRAPH:1]Der iranischen Tradition zufolge reisten die Heiligen Drei Könige, die das Jesuskind besuchten, von Saveh aus an und wurden in den Ruinen begraben. Marco Polo beschrieb die Gräber der Heiligen Drei Könige in seinem Reisebuch Il Milione.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]The alleged "relics of the Magi" (the Three Kings or the Three Wise Men in Christian tradition) were originally situated at Constantinople, but brought to Milan by Eustorgius I, the city's bishop, in 344. The relics of the Magi were taken from Milan by Holy Roman Emperor Fredrick Barbarossa and given to the Archbishop of Cologne, Rainald of Dassel in 1164. The Three Kings have since attracted a constant stream of pilgrims to Cologne. [PARAGRAPH:1]According to Iranian tradition, the Magi who visited the infant Jesus traveled from Saveh, and are buried among its ruins. Marco Polo described the tombs of the Magi in his travel book, Il Milione.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]The alleged "relics of the Magi" (the Three Kings or the Three Wise Men in Christian tradition) were originally situated at Constantinople, but brought to Milan by Eustorgius I, the city's bishop, in 344. The relics of the Magi were taken from Milan by Holy Roman Emperor Fredrick Barbarossa and given to the Archbishop of Cologne, Rainald of Dassel in 1164. The Three Kings have since attracted a constant stream of pilgrims to Cologne. [PARAGRAPH:1]According to Iranian tradition, the Magi who visited the infant Jesus traveled from Saveh, and are buried among its ruins. Marco Polo described the tombs of the Magi in his travel book, Il Milione.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>	
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIC_CROWN_OF_THORNS</Tag>
		<English>The Crown of Thorns</English>
		<French>The Crown of Thorns</French>
		<German>Die Dornenkrone</German>
		<Italian>The Crown of Thorns</Italian>
		<Spanish>The Crown of Thorns</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIC_CROWN_OF_THORNS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]In Christianity, the Crown of Thorns, one of the instruments of the Passion, was woven of thorn branches and placed on Jesus Christ before his crucifixion. It is mentioned in the Canonical gospels of Matthew (27:29), Mark (15:17), and John (19:2, 5) and is often alluded to by the early Church Fathers, such as Clement of Alexandria, Origen, and others. [PARAGRAPH:1]A few writers of the first six centuries A.D. speak of a relic known to be still in existence and venerated by the faithful. It is likely that a purported Crown of Thorns was venerated at Jerusalem from the fifth century for several hundred years. The crown, or parts of it, were later transfered to Constantinople, and a number of thorns from the crown were supposedly given to Charlemagne, St. Germain and Pope Leo III, then subsequently given away to other European rulers. The whole crown was transferred to Byzantium about 1063 until Baldwin II, the Latin Emperor of Constantinople, gave it to St. Louis of France, who built the Sainte-Chapelle to receive it. Although the relic's location changed a few more times, it eventually returned to Sainte-Chapelle and remains there to this day.</English>
		<French>[TAB]In Christianity, the Crown of Thorns, one of the instruments of the Passion, was woven of thorn branches and placed on Jesus Christ before his crucifixion. It is mentioned in the Canonical gospels of Matthew (27:29), Mark (15:17), and John (19:2, 5) and is often alluded to by the early Church Fathers, such as Clement of Alexandria, Origen, and others. [PARAGRAPH:1]A few writers of the first six centuries A.D. speak of a relic known to be still in existence and venerated by the faithful. It is likely that a purported Crown of Thorns was venerated at Jerusalem from the fifth century for several hundred years. The crown, or parts of it, were later transfered to Constantinople, and a number of thorns from the crown were supposedly given to Charlemagne, St. Germain and Pope Leo III, then subsequently given away to other European rulers. The whole crown was transferred to Byzantium about 1063 until Baldwin II, the Latin Emperor of Constantinople, gave it to St. Louis of France, who built the Sainte-Chapelle to receive it. Although the relic's location changed a few more times, it eventually returned to Sainte-Chapelle and remains there to this day.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Im Christentum wurde die Dornenkrone, eines der Instrumente der Passion, aus Dornenzweigen geflochten und Jesus Christus vor seiner Kreuzigung aufgesetzt. Es wird in den kanonischen Evangelien von Matthäus (27:29), Markus (15:17) und Johannes (19:2, 5) erwähnt und von den frühen Kirchenvätern, wie Clemens von Alexandria, Origenes, oft erwähnt. und andere. [ABSATZ:1]Einige Schriftsteller der ersten sechs Jahrhunderte n. Chr. sprechen von einer Reliquie, von der bekannt ist, dass sie noch existiert und von den Gläubigen verehrt wird. Es ist wahrscheinlich, dass in Jerusalem ab dem 5. Jahrhundert mehrere hundert Jahre lang eine angebliche Dornenkrone verehrt wurde. Die Krone oder Teile davon wurden später nach Konstantinopel überführt, und einige Dornen der Krone wurden angeblich Karl dem Großen, St. Germain und Papst Leo III. geschenkt und anschließend an andere europäische Herrscher verschenkt. Die gesamte Krone wurde um 1063 nach Byzanz übertragen, bis Balduin II., der lateinische Kaiser von Konstantinopel, sie dem heiligen Ludwig von Frankreich schenkte, der die Sainte-Chapelle errichtete, um sie zu erhalten. Obwohl sich der Standort der Reliquie noch einige Male änderte, kehrte sie schließlich nach Sainte-Chapelle zurück und verbleibt dort bis heute.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]In Christianity, the Crown of Thorns, one of the instruments of the Passion, was woven of thorn branches and placed on Jesus Christ before his crucifixion. It is mentioned in the Canonical gospels of Matthew (27:29), Mark (15:17), and John (19:2, 5) and is often alluded to by the early Church Fathers, such as Clement of Alexandria, Origen, and others. [PARAGRAPH:1]A few writers of the first six centuries A.D. speak of a relic known to be still in existence and venerated by the faithful. It is likely that a purported Crown of Thorns was venerated at Jerusalem from the fifth century for several hundred years. The crown, or parts of it, were later transfered to Constantinople, and a number of thorns from the crown were supposedly given to Charlemagne, St. Germain and Pope Leo III, then subsequently given away to other European rulers. The whole crown was transferred to Byzantium about 1063 until Baldwin II, the Latin Emperor of Constantinople, gave it to St. Louis of France, who built the Sainte-Chapelle to receive it. Although the relic's location changed a few more times, it eventually returned to Sainte-Chapelle and remains there to this day.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]In Christianity, the Crown of Thorns, one of the instruments of the Passion, was woven of thorn branches and placed on Jesus Christ before his crucifixion. It is mentioned in the Canonical gospels of Matthew (27:29), Mark (15:17), and John (19:2, 5) and is often alluded to by the early Church Fathers, such as Clement of Alexandria, Origen, and others. [PARAGRAPH:1]A few writers of the first six centuries A.D. speak of a relic known to be still in existence and venerated by the faithful. It is likely that a purported Crown of Thorns was venerated at Jerusalem from the fifth century for several hundred years. The crown, or parts of it, were later transfered to Constantinople, and a number of thorns from the crown were supposedly given to Charlemagne, St. Germain and Pope Leo III, then subsequently given away to other European rulers. The whole crown was transferred to Byzantium about 1063 until Baldwin II, the Latin Emperor of Constantinople, gave it to St. Louis of France, who built the Sainte-Chapelle to receive it. Although the relic's location changed a few more times, it eventually returned to Sainte-Chapelle and remains there to this day.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>	
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIC_BLESSED_MANTLE</Tag>
		<English>The Blessed Mantle</English>
		<French>The Blessed Mantle</French>
		<German>Der Gesegnete Mantel</German>
		<Italian>The Blessed Mantle</Italian>
		<Spanish>The Blessed Mantle</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIC_BLESSED_MANTLE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Blessed Mantle, also known as the Holy Mantle, according to tradition was given by Muhammad to the poet Kaab bin Zuheyr. The mantle is almost two yards long and made of black wool lined with a cream-colored fabric. It is one of the Islamic Sacred Relics sent to the Ottoman Sultans between the 16th century to the late 19th century.</English>
		<French>[TAB]The Blessed Mantle, also known as the Holy Mantle, according to tradition was given by Muhammad to the poet Kaab bin Zuheyr. The mantle is almost two yards long and made of black wool lined with a cream-colored fabric. It is one of the Islamic Sacred Relics sent to the Ottoman Sultans between the 16th century to the late 19th century.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Der Gesegnete Mantel, auch Heiliger Mantel genannt, wurde der Überlieferung nach von Mohammed dem Dichter Kaab bin Zuheyr geschenkt. Der Mantel ist fast zwei Meter lang und besteht aus schwarzer Wolle, gefüttert mit einem cremefarbenen Stoff. Es handelt sich um eine der heiligen islamischen Reliquien, die zwischen dem 16. und dem späten 19. Jahrhundert an die osmanischen Sultane geschickt wurden.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]The Blessed Mantle, also known as the Holy Mantle, according to tradition was given by Muhammad to the poet Kaab bin Zuheyr. The mantle is almost two yards long and made of black wool lined with a cream-colored fabric. It is one of the Islamic Sacred Relics sent to the Ottoman Sultans between the 16th century to the late 19th century.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]The Blessed Mantle, also known as the Holy Mantle, according to tradition was given by Muhammad to the poet Kaab bin Zuheyr. The mantle is almost two yards long and made of black wool lined with a cream-colored fabric. It is one of the Islamic Sacred Relics sent to the Ottoman Sultans between the 16th century to the late 19th century.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>	
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIC_HOLY_BANNER</Tag>
		<English>The Holy Banner</English>
		<French>The Holy Banner</French>
		<German>Das Heilige Banner</German>
		<Italian>The Holy Banner</Italian>
		<Spanish>The Holy Banner</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIC_HOLY_BANNER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The battle standard of Muhammad, known in Turkish as Sancak-i Serif, was believed to have served as the curtain over the entrance of his wife Aisha's tent. According to another tradition, the standard had been part of the turban of Buraydah ibn al-Khasib, an enemy who was ordered to attack Muhammad, but instead bowed to him, unwound his turban and affixed it to his spear, dedicating it and himself to Muhammad's service. [PARAGRAPH:1]Selim I acquired it, and had it taken to the Grand Mosque of Damascus where it was to be carried during the annual Hajj pilgrimage to Mecca. Realising its political possibilities, Murad III had it sent to Hungary as an incentive to his army. [PARAGRAPH:1]In 1595, Muhammad III had it brought to Topkapi Palace, where it was sewn into another standard, alleged to be Umar's, and together they were encased in a rosewood box, inlaid with gems including tortoiseshell and mother of pearl. The keys to the box were traditionally held by the Kislar Agha. [PARAGRAPH:1]It became associated with the Ottoman Empire, and was exhibited whenever the Sultan or Grand Vizier appeared before the field army, at the 1826 Auspicious Incident and at the outset of Turkey's entrance into World War I.</English>
		<French>[TAB]The battle standard of Muhammad, known in Turkish as Sancak-i Serif, was believed to have served as the curtain over the entrance of his wife Aisha's tent. According to another tradition, the standard had been part of the turban of Buraydah ibn al-Khasib, an enemy who was ordered to attack Muhammad, but instead bowed to him, unwound his turban and affixed it to his spear, dedicating it and himself to Muhammad's service. [PARAGRAPH:1]Selim I acquired it, and had it taken to the Grand Mosque of Damascus where it was to be carried during the annual Hajj pilgrimage to Mecca. Realising its political possibilities, Murad III had it sent to Hungary as an incentive to his army. [PARAGRAPH:1]In 1595, Muhammad III had it brought to Topkapi Palace, where it was sewn into another standard, alleged to be Umar's, and together they were encased in a rosewood box, inlaid with gems including tortoiseshell and mother of pearl. The keys to the box were traditionally held by the Kislar Agha. [PARAGRAPH:1]It became associated with the Ottoman Empire, and was exhibited whenever the Sultan or Grand Vizier appeared before the field army, at the 1826 Auspicious Incident and at the outset of Turkey's entrance into World War I.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Es wurde angenommen, dass die Kampfstandarte Mohammeds, auf Türkisch Sancak-i Serif genannt, als Vorhang über dem Eingang des Zeltes seiner Frau Aisha diente. Einer anderen Überlieferung zufolge war die Standarte Teil des Turbans von Buraydah ibn al-Khasib gewesen, einem Feind, dem befohlen wurde, Mohammed anzugreifen, sich aber stattdessen vor ihm verneigte, seinen Turban abwickelte und ihn an seinem Speer befestigte, um ihn und sich selbst zu weihen Mohammeds Dienst. [PARAGRAPH:1] Selim I. erwarb es und ließ es zur Großen Moschee von Damaskus bringen, wo es während der jährlichen Hadsch-Pilgerreise nach Mekka getragen werden sollte. Murad III. erkannte seine politischen Möglichkeiten und ließ es als Anreiz für seine Armee nach Ungarn schicken. [PARAGRAPH:1]Im Jahr 1595 ließ Mohammed III. es zum Topkapi-Palast bringen, wo es in eine andere Standarte eingenäht wurde, die angeblich Umars gehörte, und zusammen wurden sie in einer Schatulle aus Palisanderholz eingeschlossen, die mit Edelsteinen wie Schildpatt und Perlmutt eingelegt war. Die Schlüssel zur Schatulle befanden sich traditionell im Besitz der Kislar Agha. [PARAGRAPH:1]Es wurde mit dem Osmanischen Reich in Verbindung gebracht und immer dann ausgestellt, wenn der Sultan oder Großwesir vor der Feldarmee erschien, beim glücklichen Vorfall von 1826 und zu Beginn des Eintritts der Türkei in den Ersten Weltkrieg.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]The battle standard of Muhammad, known in Turkish as Sancak-i Serif, was believed to have served as the curtain over the entrance of his wife Aisha's tent. According to another tradition, the standard had been part of the turban of Buraydah ibn al-Khasib, an enemy who was ordered to attack Muhammad, but instead bowed to him, unwound his turban and affixed it to his spear, dedicating it and himself to Muhammad's service. [PARAGRAPH:1]Selim I acquired it, and had it taken to the Grand Mosque of Damascus where it was to be carried during the annual Hajj pilgrimage to Mecca. Realising its political possibilities, Murad III had it sent to Hungary as an incentive to his army. [PARAGRAPH:1]In 1595, Muhammad III had it brought to Topkapi Palace, where it was sewn into another standard, alleged to be Umar's, and together they were encased in a rosewood box, inlaid with gems including tortoiseshell and mother of pearl. The keys to the box were traditionally held by the Kislar Agha. [PARAGRAPH:1]It became associated with the Ottoman Empire, and was exhibited whenever the Sultan or Grand Vizier appeared before the field army, at the 1826 Auspicious Incident and at the outset of Turkey's entrance into World War I.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]The battle standard of Muhammad, known in Turkish as Sancak-i Serif, was believed to have served as the curtain over the entrance of his wife Aisha's tent. According to another tradition, the standard had been part of the turban of Buraydah ibn al-Khasib, an enemy who was ordered to attack Muhammad, but instead bowed to him, unwound his turban and affixed it to his spear, dedicating it and himself to Muhammad's service. [PARAGRAPH:1]Selim I acquired it, and had it taken to the Grand Mosque of Damascus where it was to be carried during the annual Hajj pilgrimage to Mecca. Realising its political possibilities, Murad III had it sent to Hungary as an incentive to his army. [PARAGRAPH:1]In 1595, Muhammad III had it brought to Topkapi Palace, where it was sewn into another standard, alleged to be Umar's, and together they were encased in a rosewood box, inlaid with gems including tortoiseshell and mother of pearl. The keys to the box were traditionally held by the Kislar Agha. [PARAGRAPH:1]It became associated with the Ottoman Empire, and was exhibited whenever the Sultan or Grand Vizier appeared before the field army, at the 1826 Auspicious Incident and at the outset of Turkey's entrance into World War I.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>	
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIC_SACRED_SEAL</Tag>
		<English>The Sacred Seal</English>
		<French>The Sacred Seal</French>
		<German>Das Heilige Siegel</German>
		<Italian>The Sacred Seal</Italian>
		<Spanish>The Sacred Seal</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIC_SACRED_SEAL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Sacred seal, or Muhr-u Serif, was reported by the 17th-century French explorer Jean-Baptiste Tavernier, who said it was kept in a small ebony box in a niche cut in the wall by the foot of a divan in the relic room at Topkapi. [PARAGRAPH:1]The seal itself is encased in crystal, approximately 3" x 4", with a border of ivory. It has been used as recently as the 17th century to stamp documents.</English>
		<French>[TAB]The Sacred seal, or Muhr-u Serif, was reported by the 17th-century French explorer Jean-Baptiste Tavernier, who said it was kept in a small ebony box in a niche cut in the wall by the foot of a divan in the relic room at Topkapi. [PARAGRAPH:1]The seal itself is encased in crystal, approximately 3" x 4", with a border of ivory. It has been used as recently as the 17th century to stamp documents.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Das Heilige Siegel, oder Muhr-u Serif, wurde vom französischen Entdecker Jean-Baptiste Tavernier aus dem 17. Jahrhundert berichtet, der sagte, es sei in einer kleinen Ebenholzkiste in einer Nische aufbewahrt worden, die am Fuß eines Diwans in die Wand geschnitten war im Reliquienraum am Topkapi. [PARAGRAPH:1]Das Siegel selbst ist in Kristall eingefasst, etwa 3" x 4", mit einem Rand aus Elfenbein. Noch im 17. Jahrhundert wurde es zum Stempeln von Dokumenten verwendet.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]The Sacred seal, or Muhr-u Serif, was reported by the 17th-century French explorer Jean-Baptiste Tavernier, who said it was kept in a small ebony box in a niche cut in the wall by the foot of a divan in the relic room at Topkapi. [PARAGRAPH:1]The seal itself is encased in crystal, approximately 3" x 4", with a border of ivory. It has been used as recently as the 17th century to stamp documents.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]The Sacred seal, or Muhr-u Serif, was reported by the 17th-century French explorer Jean-Baptiste Tavernier, who said it was kept in a small ebony box in a niche cut in the wall by the foot of a divan in the relic room at Topkapi. [PARAGRAPH:1]The seal itself is encased in crystal, approximately 3" x 4", with a border of ivory. It has been used as recently as the 17th century to stamp documents.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIC_SWORD_OF_ALI</Tag>
		<English>The Sword of Ali</English>
		<French>The Sword of Ali</French>
		<German>Das Schwert Alis</German>
		<Italian>The Sword of Ali</Italian>
		<Spanish>The Sword of Ali</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIC_SWORD_OF_ALI_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Zulfiqar, or Dhu al-Fiqar, is the sword of the Islamic leader Ali, allegedly bestowed on him by the angel Gabriel. Over time, it has become one of the symbols of the Shia branch of Islam.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Zulfiqar, or Dhu al-Fiqar, is the sword of the Islamic leader Ali, allegedly bestowed on him by the angel Gabriel. Over time, it has become one of the symbols of the Shia branch of Islam.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Zulfiqar oder Dhu al-Fiqar ist das Schwert des islamischen Führers Ali, das ihm angeblich vom Engel Gabriel verliehen wurde. Im Laufe der Zeit wurde es zu einem der Symbole des schiitischen Zweigs des Islam.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Zulfiqar, or Dhu al-Fiqar, is the sword of the Islamic leader Ali, allegedly bestowed on him by the angel Gabriel. Over time, it has become one of the symbols of the Shia branch of Islam.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]Zulfiqar, or Dhu al-Fiqar, is the sword of the Islamic leader Ali, allegedly bestowed on him by the angel Gabriel. Over time, it has become one of the symbols of the Shia branch of Islam.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIC_CLOAK_OF_THE_PROPHET</Tag>
		<English>The Cloak of the Prophet</English>
		<French>The Cloak of the Prophet</French>
		<German>Der Umhang des Propheten</German>
		<Italian>The Cloak of the Prophet</Italian>
		<Spanish>The Cloak of the Prophet</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIC_CLOAK_OF_THE_PROPHET_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Cloak of the Prophet is a cloak that was once worn by Islam's Prophet Muhammad. It is currently kept in a shrine in Kandahar, Afghanistan. The relic was most likely brought there from Bukhara by Ahmad Shah Durrani in 18th century.</English>
		<French>[TAB]The Cloak of the Prophet is a cloak that was once worn by Islam's Prophet Muhammad. It is currently kept in a shrine in Kandahar, Afghanistan. The relic was most likely brought there from Bukhara by Ahmad Shah Durrani in 18th century.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Der Umhang des Propheten ist ein Umhang, der einst vom islamischen Propheten Muhammad getragen wurde. Es wird derzeit in einem Schrein (Kirka Sharif) in Kandahar, Afghanistan, aufbewahrt. Die Reliquie wurde höchstwahrscheinlich im 18. Jahrhundert von Ahmad Schah Durrani aus Buchara dorthin gebracht.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]The Cloak of the Prophet is a cloak that was once worn by Islam's Prophet Muhammad. It is currently kept in a shrine in Kandahar, Afghanistan. The relic was most likely brought there from Bukhara by Ahmad Shah Durrani in 18th century.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]The Cloak of the Prophet is a cloak that was once worn by Islam's Prophet Muhammad. It is currently kept in a shrine in Kandahar, Afghanistan. The relic was most likely brought there from Bukhara by Ahmad Shah Durrani in 18th century.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>	
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIC_BEARD_OF_MUHAMMAD</Tag>
		<English>The Beard of Muhammad</English>
		<French>The Beard of Muhammad</French>
		<German>Der Bart Mohammeds</German>
		<Italian>The Beard of Muhammad</Italian>
		<Spanish>The Beard of Muhammad</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIC_BEARD_OF_MUHAMMAD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Known as the Sakal-i Serif, the beard was said to have been shaved from Muhammad's face after death, by his favoured barber Salman in the presence of Abu Bakr, Ali and several others. Individual hairs were later taken away, but the beard itself is kept in a glass reliquarium.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Known as the Sakal-i Serif, the beard was said to have been shaved from Muhammad's face after death, by his favoured barber Salman in the presence of Abu Bakr, Ali and several others. Individual hairs were later taken away, but the beard itself is kept in a glass reliquarium.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Der als Sakal-i Serif bekannte Bart soll nach dem Tod Mohammeds von seinem Lieblingsfriseur Salman im Beisein von Abu Bakr, Ali und mehreren anderen aus dem Gesicht rasiert worden sein. Einzelne Haare wurden später entfernt, der Bart selbst wird jedoch in einem gläsernen Reliquiarium aufbewahrt.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Known as the Sakal-i Serif, the beard was said to have been shaved from Muhammad's face after death, by his favoured barber Salman in the presence of Abu Bakr, Ali and several others. Individual hairs were later taken away, but the beard itself is kept in a glass reliquarium.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]Known as the Sakal-i Serif, the beard was said to have been shaved from Muhammad's face after death, by his favoured barber Salman in the presence of Abu Bakr, Ali and several others. Individual hairs were later taken away, but the beard itself is kept in a glass reliquarium.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>