<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<!-- ********************************************************************* -->
	<!-- Leaders (names, civilopedia entries, diplo texts) -->
	<!-- ********************************************************************* -->
	<!-- ******************** Leaders, names ******************************* -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_MAGYAR_Koppany</Tag>
		<English>Koppány</English>
		<French>Koppány</French>
		<German>Koppány</German>
		<Italian>Koppány</Italian>
		<Spanish>Koppány</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Koppány</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<!-- ******************** Leaders, civilopedia entry ******************************* -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_MAGYAR_Koppany_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Koppány[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Hungarian prince[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] ca. 950 - 998[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Koppány was the son of Tar Zerind, a relative of the hungarian Grand Prince Géza. After Gézas death, Koppány claimed the throne based on the agnatic seniority - a principle of inheritance common for steppe peoples where the oldest living member of the dinasty is the successor on the throne. Koppány also wanted to marry Sarolt, the widow of Géza, based on old hungarian steppe traditions. In contrast, the family of Géza claimed the throne for Vajk, the latter Stephen or István I., based on the primogeniture which was common in western europe and where the firstborn son of the former monarch inherits the throne.[NEWLINE][TAB]According to the hungarian chronicles, Koppány was the son of Tar Zerind, whos heritage is unclear. Because of Koppány was able to claim the throne relying on the agnatic seniority and wanted to marry the dead Grand Prince' widow (Levirate marriage), Sarolt, he certainly was a descendant of Árpád. Because of the locations bearing his name are all close to Tevels and Tormás' estates, it is likely that Tarhos was the oldest son of Árpád, whos son was Tevel and grandson was Tar Zerind making Koppány Árpáds greatgreat-grandson. There is also another point of view saying that Tar Zerind was Gézas younger brother Mihály, while Koppány was Szár László, based on that both where baptized, even if only feignedly.[NEWLINE][TAB]Till 972 - when Géza adopted christianity - the succession to the throne probably followed the principle of agnatic seniority. Géza could succeed to grand prince Taksony, because the likely heir Tar Zerind died while Taksony was still alive making Géza the oldest member of the Árpád dinasty. After Taksony died, Géza became prince and his younger brother Mihály was the heir, who owned the dukátus (land given to the heir according to old turkic traditions).[NEWLINE][TAB]Tension raised after Vajk was born (between 975 and 980) and Mihály died making Koppány the heir to the throne according to the agnatic seniority. Instead, Géza gave the dukátus of Nyitra to Vajk, who also got the estate of Tolna same time, which was the heirs property till the 12th century. At that time or earlier, Koppány got Somogy - which then reached till the todays Zagreb - having to renounce on all other demands. The tension was obvious when Géza settled a chain of pecheneg settlements on the banks of the Sárvíz between his and Koppánys lands. At that time, the Pechenegs task was to protect the borderland, so they were usually settled near the borderlines. Somogy was also surrounded by settlements of Székelys as well as of members of the tribes of the Kér and Keszi.[NEWLINE][TAB]Grand prince Géze died in the fall of 997. According to nomad traditions, the power was held by the wife of the grand prince, Sarolt, till the new prince would take over the reign. Koppány claimed the throne based on the agnatic seniorityand and according to nomad traditions wanted to marry Sarolt, so he started to siege Veszprém, where her seat was located.[NEWLINE][TAB]When István heared about his fathers death, he called together his leaders and after he heared about Koppánys rebellion, he requested support from his brother-in-law, his wife Gizellas brother Henrik, duke of Bavaria. He went to Esztergom where he was equipped with the grand prince' sword through a christian ritual.[NEWLINE][TAB]When he heard that István was closing, Koppány abbandoned the siege and went towards István. The decisive battle took place somewhere between Veszprém and Várpalota, probably at Sóly.[NEWLINE][TAB]Koppány also died in the bloody battle and according to the chronical traditions his body was quartered and was hang up at the countries four castles (Gyõr, Veszprém, Esztergom and Gyulafehérvár). The localities where likely been chosen by whom István and Sarolt wanted to warn. István became the legitime ruler and didn't have to take up arms because of a rebellion for 6 years. After his victory, István consolidated the new hungarian christian state that his father Géza founded.[NEWLINE][TAB]Nowadays, Koppánys rebellion is topic of a popular hungarian rock opera called 'István, the king'.</English>
		<French>[H1]Koppány[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Hungarian prince[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] ca. 950 - 998[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Koppány was the son of Tar Zerind, a relative of the hungarian Grand Prince Géza. After Gézas death, Koppány claimed the throne based on the agnatic seniority - a principle of inheritance common for steppe peoples where the oldest living member of the dinasty is the successor on the throne. Koppány also wanted to marry Sarolt, the widow of Géza, based on old hungarian steppe traditions. In contrast, the family of Géza claimed the throne for Vajk, the latter Stephen or István I., based on the primogeniture which was common in western europe and where the firstborn son of the former monarch inherits the throne.[NEWLINE][TAB]According to the hungarian chronicles, Koppány was the son of Tar Zerind, whos heritage is unclear. Because of Koppány was able to claim the throne relying on the agnatic seniority and wanted to marry the dead Grand Prince' widow (Levirate marriage), Sarolt, he certainly was a descendant of Árpád. Because of the locations bearing his name are all close to Tevels and Tormás' estates, it is likely that Tarhos was the oldest son of Árpád, whos son was Tevel and grandson was Tar Zerind making Koppány Árpáds greatgreat-grandson. There is also another point of view saying that Tar Zerind was Gézas younger brother Mihály, while Koppány was Szár László, based on that both where baptized, even if only feignedly.[NEWLINE][TAB]Till 972 - when Géza adopted christianity - the succession to the throne probably followed the principle of agnatic seniority. Géza could succeed to grand prince Taksony, because the likely heir Tar Zerind died while Taksony was still alive making Géza the oldest member of the Árpád dinasty. After Taksony died, Géza became prince and his younger brother Mihály was the heir, who owned the dukátus (land given to the heir according to old turkic traditions).[NEWLINE][TAB]Tension raised after Vajk was born (between 975 and 980) and Mihály died making Koppány the heir to the throne according to the agnatic seniority. Instead, Géza gave the dukátus of Nyitra to Vajk, who also got the estate of Tolna same time, which was the heirs property till the 12th century. At that time or earlier, Koppány got Somogy - which then reached till the todays Zagreb - having to renounce on all other demands. The tension was obvious when Géza settled a chain of pecheneg settlements on the banks of the Sárvíz between his and Koppánys lands. At that time, the Pechenegs task was to protect the borderland, so they were usually settled near the borderlines. Somogy was also surrounded by settlements of Székelys as well as of members of the tribes of the Kér and Keszi.[NEWLINE][TAB]Grand prince Géze died in the fall of 997. According to nomad traditions, the power was held by the wife of the grand prince, Sarolt, till the new prince would take over the reign. Koppány claimed the throne based on the agnatic seniorityand and according to nomad traditions wanted to marry Sarolt, so he started to siege Veszprém, where her seat was located.[NEWLINE][TAB]When István heared about his fathers death, he called together his leaders and after he heared about Koppánys rebellion, he requested support from his brother-in-law, his wife Gizellas brother Henrik, duke of Bavaria. He went to Esztergom where he was equipped with the grand prince' sword through a christian ritual.[NEWLINE][TAB]When he heard that István was closing, Koppány abbandoned the siege and went towards István. The decisive battle took place somewhere between Veszprém and Várpalota, probably at Sóly.[NEWLINE][TAB]Koppány also died in the bloody battle and according to the chronical traditions his body was quartered and was hang up at the countries four castles (Gyõr, Veszprém, Esztergom and Gyulafehérvár). The localities where likely been chosen by whom István and Sarolt wanted to warn. István became the legitime ruler and didn't have to take up arms because of a rebellion for 6 years. After his victory, István consolidated the new hungarian christian state that his father Géza founded.[NEWLINE][TAB]Nowadays, Koppánys rebellion is topic of a popular hungarian rock opera called 'István, the king'.</French>
		<German>[H1]Koppány[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Ungarischer Fürst[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lebte:[\BOLD] etwa 950 - 998[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Koppány war der Sohn von Tar Zerind, eines Verwandten des ungarischen Großfürsten Géza. Nach dessen Tod beanspruchte Koppány den Thron gemäß dem Senioratsprinzip (das älteste lebende Mitglied der Herrscherfamilie erbt den Thron) und forderte gemäß den alten ungarischen Steppentriten Sarolt, die Witwe des Großfürsten, zur Frau. Die Familie Gézas beanspruchte allerdings den Thron für dessen Sohn Vajk, dem späteren Stephan  beziehungsweise István I., entsprechend der im Westen üblichen Primogenitur (der erstgeborene Sohn erbt den Thron).[NEWLINE][TAB]Laut der ungarischen Chronik war er der Sohn des Tar Zerind, dessen Abstammung nicht geklärt ist. Weil Koppány aber den Thron auf Grundlage des Senioratsprinzip beanspruchen konnte und Sarolt, die Witwe des Großfürsten und Mutter des späteren Stephan I., zur Frau forderte, kann davon ausgegangen werden, dass er ein Nachfahre Árpáds war. Da die Siedlung, die seinen Namen tragen, an die Ländereien von Tevel und Tormás grenzen, ist es wahrscheinlich, dass Tar Zerind der Sohn Tevels war, dessen Vater Tarhos der erstgeborene Sohn Árpáds, Koppány also der Ururenkel Árpáds war. Einer anderen Meinung nach war Tar Zerind Mihály, der jüngere Bruder Gézas. Koppány wäre dann Szár László, vorausgesetzt beide hätten sich taufen lassen, wenn auch nur dem Schein nach.[NEWLINE][TAB]Vor 972 - als Géza zum Christentum übertrat - folgte die ungarische Thronfolge wahrscheinlich dem Senioratsprinzip. Nach dem Tod des Großfürsten Taksonys konnte Géza ihm wahrscheinlich deshalb auf dem Thron folgen, weil der ursprüngliche Thronfolger Tar Zerind noch zu Taksonys Lebzeiten starb, so wurde also Géza das älteste lebende Mitglied der Árpáddynastie. Als Taksony starb wurde also Géze Großfürst und dessen jünger Bruder Mihály der Thronfolger, der die Dukátus (Ländereien, die immer im Besitz des Thronfolgers waren) besaß.[NEWLINE][TAB]Die Spannungen bildeten sich wahrscheinlich nach der Geburt Istváns, zwischen 975 und 980, und nach dem Tod Mihálys, als nach Senioratsprinzip Koppány der Thronfolger hätte werden müssen, Géza die Dukátus von Nitra seinem Sohn gab. Zur selben Zeit bekam István auch die Tolnaer Länderein, die bis zum 12. Jahrhundert Besitz des Thronfolgers waren. Spätestens jetzt, wahrscheinlich schon eher, erhielt Koppány Somogy, das damals noch bis zum heutigen Zagreb reichte - jedoch musste er auf alle übrigen Ansprüche verzichten. Deutlich wurden die Spannungen als Géza zwischen seine und die Ländereien Koppánys entlang der Sárvíz Petschenegen ansiedelte. Zu der Zeit war die Aufgabe der Petschenegen vorallem der Grenzschutz, also wurden sie in Grenznähe angesiedelt. Géze grenzte Somogy auch anderenorts ab, indem er Székler und Mitglieder der Stämme Kér und Keszi ansiedeln ließ.[NEWLINE][TAB]Großfürst Géza starb im Herbst 997. Bis zur Kür des neuen Großfürsten lag die Macht nach nomadischen Bräuchen nun in den Händen der Witwe, Sarolt, deren Sitz Veszprém war. Koppány beanspruchte nun nach dem Senioratsprinzip den Thron und gemäß dem Levirat den Eheschluss mit Sarolt und begann Veszprém zu belagern.[NEWLINE][TAB]Als er vom Tod seines Vaters erfuhr, ließ István seine Anführer in Esztergom versammeln. Als ihn die Nachricht des Aufstandes Koppánys erreichte, bat er seinen Schwager Henrik von Bayern, Bruder seiner Frau Gizella, um Hilfe und begab sich selbst auch nach Esztergom. In einem kirchlichem Ritual erhielt er dort das Schwert des Großfürsten.[NEWLINE][TAB]Als er davon erfur, dass sich István näherte, brach Koppány die Belagerung Veszprém ab und zog der Armee Istváns entgegen. Irgendwo zwischen Veszprém und Várpalota, vermutlich an der Sóly, kam es zur Entscheidungsschlacht.[NEWLINE][TAB]In der blutigen Schlacht fiel auch Koppány und nach den Traditionen der Kroniken wurde sein Körper gevierteilt und an den vier Burgen des Landes - Gyõrben, Veszprémben, Esztergomban und Gyulafehérvár - aufgehängt. Bei der Wahl der Orte könnte auch eine Rolle gespielt haben, wen István und Sarolt warnen wollten. Danach wurde István anerkannter Großfürst und musste 6 Jahre lang nicht mehr wegen eines Aufstandes zur Waffe greifen. Nach seinem Sieg festigte er den neuen christlichen ungarischen Staat, dessen Ausbau sein Vater Géza begonnen hatte.[NEWLINE][TAB]Heute erzählt eine beliebte ungarische Rockoper - István, der König - vom Aufstand Koppánys.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Koppány[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Hungarian prince[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] ca. 950 - 998[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Koppány was the son of Tar Zerind, a relative of the hungarian Grand Prince Géza. After Gézas death, Koppány claimed the throne based on the agnatic seniority - a principle of inheritance common for steppe peoples where the oldest living member of the dinasty is the successor on the throne. Koppány also wanted to marry Sarolt, the widow of Géza, based on old hungarian steppe traditions. In contrast, the family of Géza claimed the throne for Vajk, the latter Stephen or István I., based on the primogeniture which was common in western europe and where the firstborn son of the former monarch inherits the throne.[NEWLINE][TAB]According to the hungarian chronicles, Koppány was the son of Tar Zerind, whos heritage is unclear. Because of Koppány was able to claim the throne relying on the agnatic seniority and wanted to marry the dead Grand Prince' widow (Levirate marriage), Sarolt, he certainly was a descendant of Árpád. Because of the locations bearing his name are all close to Tevels and Tormás' estates, it is likely that Tarhos was the oldest son of Árpád, whos son was Tevel and grandson was Tar Zerind making Koppány Árpáds greatgreat-grandson. There is also another point of view saying that Tar Zerind was Gézas younger brother Mihály, while Koppány was Szár László, based on that both where baptized, even if only feignedly.[NEWLINE][TAB]Till 972 - when Géza adopted christianity - the succession to the throne probably followed the principle of agnatic seniority. Géza could succeed to grand prince Taksony, because the likely heir Tar Zerind died while Taksony was still alive making Géza the oldest member of the Árpád dinasty. After Taksony died, Géza became prince and his younger brother Mihály was the heir, who owned the dukátus (land given to the heir according to old turkic traditions).[NEWLINE][TAB]Tension raised after Vajk was born (between 975 and 980) and Mihály died making Koppány the heir to the throne according to the agnatic seniority. Instead, Géza gave the dukátus of Nyitra to Vajk, who also got the estate of Tolna same time, which was the heirs property till the 12th century. At that time or earlier, Koppány got Somogy - which then reached till the todays Zagreb - having to renounce on all other demands. The tension was obvious when Géza settled a chain of pecheneg settlements on the banks of the Sárvíz between his and Koppánys lands. At that time, the Pechenegs task was to protect the borderland, so they were usually settled near the borderlines. Somogy was also surrounded by settlements of Székelys as well as of members of the tribes of the Kér and Keszi.[NEWLINE][TAB]Grand prince Géze died in the fall of 997. According to nomad traditions, the power was held by the wife of the grand prince, Sarolt, till the new prince would take over the reign. Koppány claimed the throne based on the agnatic seniorityand and according to nomad traditions wanted to marry Sarolt, so he started to siege Veszprém, where her seat was located.[NEWLINE][TAB]When István heared about his fathers death, he called together his leaders and after he heared about Koppánys rebellion, he requested support from his brother-in-law, his wife Gizellas brother Henrik, duke of Bavaria. He went to Esztergom where he was equipped with the grand prince' sword through a christian ritual.[NEWLINE][TAB]When he heard that István was closing, Koppány abbandoned the siege and went towards István. The decisive battle took place somewhere between Veszprém and Várpalota, probably at Sóly.[NEWLINE][TAB]Koppány also died in the bloody battle and according to the chronical traditions his body was quartered and was hang up at the countries four castles (Gyõr, Veszprém, Esztergom and Gyulafehérvár). The localities where likely been chosen by whom István and Sarolt wanted to warn. István became the legitime ruler and didn't have to take up arms because of a rebellion for 6 years. After his victory, István consolidated the new hungarian christian state that his father Géza founded.[NEWLINE][TAB]Nowadays, Koppánys rebellion is topic of a popular hungarian rock opera called 'István, the king'.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Koppány[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Hungarian prince[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] ca. 950 - 998[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Koppány was the son of Tar Zerind, a relative of the hungarian Grand Prince Géza. After Gézas death, Koppány claimed the throne based on the agnatic seniority - a principle of inheritance common for steppe peoples where the oldest living member of the dinasty is the successor on the throne. Koppány also wanted to marry Sarolt, the widow of Géza, based on old hungarian steppe traditions. In contrast, the family of Géza claimed the throne for Vajk, the latter Stephen or István I., based on the primogeniture which was common in western europe and where the firstborn son of the former monarch inherits the throne.[NEWLINE][TAB]According to the hungarian chronicles, Koppány was the son of Tar Zerind, whos heritage is unclear. Because of Koppány was able to claim the throne relying on the agnatic seniority and wanted to marry the dead Grand Prince' widow (Levirate marriage), Sarolt, he certainly was a descendant of Árpád. Because of the locations bearing his name are all close to Tevels and Tormás' estates, it is likely that Tarhos was the oldest son of Árpád, whos son was Tevel and grandson was Tar Zerind making Koppány Árpáds greatgreat-grandson. There is also another point of view saying that Tar Zerind was Gézas younger brother Mihály, while Koppány was Szár László, based on that both where baptized, even if only feignedly.[NEWLINE][TAB]Till 972 - when Géza adopted christianity - the succession to the throne probably followed the principle of agnatic seniority. Géza could succeed to grand prince Taksony, because the likely heir Tar Zerind died while Taksony was still alive making Géza the oldest member of the Árpád dinasty. After Taksony died, Géza became prince and his younger brother Mihály was the heir, who owned the dukátus (land given to the heir according to old turkic traditions).[NEWLINE][TAB]Tension raised after Vajk was born (between 975 and 980) and Mihály died making Koppány the heir to the throne according to the agnatic seniority. Instead, Géza gave the dukátus of Nyitra to Vajk, who also got the estate of Tolna same time, which was the heirs property till the 12th century. At that time or earlier, Koppány got Somogy - which then reached till the todays Zagreb - having to renounce on all other demands. The tension was obvious when Géza settled a chain of pecheneg settlements on the banks of the Sárvíz between his and Koppánys lands. At that time, the Pechenegs task was to protect the borderland, so they were usually settled near the borderlines. Somogy was also surrounded by settlements of Székelys as well as of members of the tribes of the Kér and Keszi.[NEWLINE][TAB]Grand prince Géze died in the fall of 997. According to nomad traditions, the power was held by the wife of the grand prince, Sarolt, till the new prince would take over the reign. Koppány claimed the throne based on the agnatic seniorityand and according to nomad traditions wanted to marry Sarolt, so he started to siege Veszprém, where her seat was located.[NEWLINE][TAB]When István heared about his fathers death, he called together his leaders and after he heared about Koppánys rebellion, he requested support from his brother-in-law, his wife Gizellas brother Henrik, duke of Bavaria. He went to Esztergom where he was equipped with the grand prince' sword through a christian ritual.[NEWLINE][TAB]When he heard that István was closing, Koppány abbandoned the siege and went towards István. The decisive battle took place somewhere between Veszprém and Várpalota, probably at Sóly.[NEWLINE][TAB]Koppány also died in the bloody battle and according to the chronical traditions his body was quartered and was hang up at the countries four castles (Gyõr, Veszprém, Esztergom and Gyulafehérvár). The localities where likely been chosen by whom István and Sarolt wanted to warn. István became the legitime ruler and didn't have to take up arms because of a rebellion for 6 years. After his victory, István consolidated the new hungarian christian state that his father Géza founded.[NEWLINE][TAB]Nowadays, Koppánys rebellion is topic of a popular hungarian rock opera called 'István, the king'.</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>[H1]Koppány[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Magyar fejedelem[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Élt:[\BOLD] kb. 950 - 998[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Háttér:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Koppány Géza magyar fejedelem rokonának, Tar Zerindnek a fia volt, aki Géza halála után a sztyeppei népekre jellemzõ szeniorátus elve alapján magának követelte a hatalmat, és régi magyar sztyeppei szokás szerint feleségül akarta venni Sarolt fejedelemasszonyt, Géza feleségét. Géza családja viszont a nyugatról származó primogenitúra elve alapján Vajknak, a késõbbi Szent István királynak követelte a hatalmat.[NEWLINE][TAB]A Magyar Krónika szerint Tar Zerind fia volt, akinek származását nem ismerjük biztosan. De mivel Koppány felléphetett a fejedelmi cím megszerzéséért a szeniorátus elvére hivatkozva és el akarta venni az elhunyt fejedelem feleségét (levirátus), Saroltot, a késõbbi I. István anyját, ezért minden bizonnyal Árpád fejedelem leszármazottja volt. Mivel a nevét viselõ települések és birtokok Tevel és Tormás birtokai mellett fekszenek, valószínûleg Árpád legidõsebb fiának, Tarhosnak volt fia Tevel, unokája Tar Zerind, s így dédunokája Koppány, vagyis Koppány Árpád ükunokája volt. Más elmélet is létezik, amelyik Tar Zerindet Géza öccsével, Mihállyal, Koppányt pedig Szár Lászlóval azonosítja, arra alapozva, hogy õk is megkeresztelkedtek, még ha csak színleg is.[NEWLINE][TAB]972 - amikor Géza nagyfejedelem felvette a kereszténységet - elõtt a magyar trónutódlás valószínûleg a szeniorátus elvének megfelelõen zajlott. Taksony nagyfejedelem után azért következhetett Géza, mert a Taksony idején valószínû trónörökös Tar Zerind még Taksony életében meghalt, és így Géza lett a rangidõs Árpád-házi herceg. Taksony halálakor Géza lett a nagyfejedelem és valószínûleg öccse, Mihály a trónörökös, aki a dukátusokat birtokolta.[NEWLINE][TAB]A feszültség Vajk, a késõbbi I. István megszületése, ami 975-980 környékére tehetõ, és Mihály halála után kezdõdhetett, amikor a szeniorátus rendje szerint Koppánynak kellett volna elõlépnie trónörökössé, Géza azonban a nyitrai dukátust fiának adta. István ugyanekkor megkapta a tolnai uradalmat, ami a 12. századig a trónörökös birtoka volt. Koppány legkésõbb ekkor, de talán már elõbb kapta meg Somogyot - amin akkoriban a mai Zágrábig nyúló területet kell érteni - és ennek fejébe le kellett mondania a többi területi igényérõl. A feszültséget jelzi, hogy Géza a saját és Koppány országának határára a Sárvíz mentén besenyõ falvak láncolatát telepítette. A besenyõk ekkoriban határõrizeti feladatokat láttak el, ezért rendszerint az országhatárra helyezték õket. Somogyot más oldalról is körülkerítette Géza, Baranya felõl székely falvakkal, Zala, Tolna, fejér és Veszprém felõl pedig a Kér és Keszi törzsbeliekkel, valamint egyéb katonai segédnépekkel.[NEWLINE][TAB]Géza nagyfejedelem 997 õszén meghalt. Ekkor nomád szokás szerint a hatalom az új nagyfejedelem felavatásáig Sarolt fejedelemasszony kezébe került, akinek székhelye Veszprém volt. Koppány, ugyancsak nomád szokás, a szeniorátus elve értelmében magának követelte a hatalmat és vele ugyancsak nomád szokás, a levirátus értelmében az elhunyt nagyfejedelem feleségét, Saroltot, és ostrom alá vette Veszprémet.[NEWLINE][TAB]Apja halálhírére István Esztergomba összehívta a fõembereket, Koppány lázadásának hírére pedig értesítette sógorát, Gizella bátyját, Henrik bajor herceget és maga is Esztergomba vonult, ahol egyházi szertartás keretében felövezték a nagyfejedelmi karddal.[NEWLINE][TAB]István közeledtének hírére Koppány felhagyott Veszprém ostromával, és István serege felé indult. A döntõ ütközetre valahol Veszprém és Várpalota között, valószínûleg Sólyon került sor.[NEWLINE][TAB]A véres csatában Koppány is meghalt, és a krónikás hagyomány szerint testét felnégyelték és kitûzték az ország négy várában, Gyõrben, Veszprémben, Esztergomban és Gyulafehérváron. A helyszínek kiválasztásában szerepet játszhatott, hogy kiket akart István és Sarolt figyelmeztetni. István ezután elismert nagyfejedelem lett, 6 évig nem kellett újabb lázadás miatt fegyverhez nyúlnia. Gyõzelme után, István megszilárdította az új keresztény magyar államot, aminek kiépítését apja, Géza kezdte el.</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
